Palmer mss., 1835-1888 LMC 1815
Lilly Library
Palmer mss.
1835-1888
Lilly Library
Palmer, Joel, 1810-1881.
Palmer, Ephraim
LMC 1815
1 folio oversize
4 Boxes 4 standard
1 bound
The Palmer mss., 1835-1888, consists of the correspondence and papers of Joel Palmer, 1810-1881, superintendent of Indian Affairs in Oregon Territory, 1853-1857, and of his brother, Ephraim Palmer, captain of Company B, 1st regiment, Oregon Infantry.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Career of Joel Palmer: born, October 4, 1810, Ontario, Canada; family moved to New York state, 1812; Joel Palmer moved to Bucks County, Pennsylvania at about sixteen years of age; moved to Laurel, Franklin County, Indiana, 1836; representative in Indiana legislature, 1843-1845; crossed plains to Oregon, 1845; commissary-general of volunteer forces in Cayuse War, 1847; led a company to California gold mines, 1848 and 1849; laid out Dayton, Oregon, in winter of 1848-1849; superintendent of Indian Affairs, Oregon Territory, 1853-1857; in gold fields of the Fraser and Thompson Rivers and in the Similkameen Valley, British Columbia as a trader, 1858-1861; opened route from Priest Rapids through Oregon and Washington to gold diggings of Okanogan, Similkameen, Rock Creek, and Upper Columbia River in British Columbia, 1860; speaker, Oregon House of Representatives, 1862; organized Columbia River Road Company to open trail for pack trains and cattle through Oregon side of Columbia river gorge, 1862; appointed brigadier-general, Oregon Militia, 1862; member Oregon Senate, 1864-1866; defeated as Republican candidate for governor of Oregon, 1870; U.S. Indian agent at Siletz Indian Reservation, 1871- 1874; died, Dayton, Oregon, June 9, 1881.
Biographical information on Joel Palmer may be found in Stanley S. Spaid's "The Later Life and Activities of General Joel Palmer," Oregon Historical Quarterly, LV: 311-332, December 1954; and Edward Evans' History of the Pacific Northwest (Portland, Oregon, 1889) II: 508. There is also biographical and genealogical material relating to Joel Palmer and his family in the first folder in the Palmer collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Scope and Content Note
Most of the papers in the collection fall within the years 1853-1874. Those before 1853 consist of Joel Palmer's naturalization certificate as a U.S. citizen, October 8, 1832, and some personal papers, 1849-1852. For 1853-January 10, 1857, the manuscripts consist almost entirely of official correspondence and papers of Joel Palmer as Superintendent of Indian Affairs. Included are his diaries for 1854 and 1856, correspondence, financial and other reports and records, and a number of bills and receipts. There are also diaries for 1860 and 1861 at which time Joel Palmer was acting as a trader in the gold fields of the Fraser and Thompson Rivers and in the Similkameen Valley, British Columbia. For 1871- 1874 the papers are those of Palmer as U.S. Indian agent at the Siletz Indian Reservation.
The manuscripts in the collection for 1864-1866 are almost entirely Ephraim Palmer's official letters and papers as captain of Company B, 1st regiment, Oregon Infantry.
Also included in the collection are an undated plat map of Dayton, Oregon; a map of a reconnaissance of the route of the Snake River expedition in 1855 by George Henry Mendell; a daguerreotype and a photograph of Joel Palmer; a daguerreotype of Joel Palmer and his second wife, Mrs. Sarah Ann (Derbyshire) Palmer; photograph of Mrs. Sarah Ann (Derbyshire) Palmer, George Abernethy, Andrew Smith, husband of Mrs. Sarah Elizabeth (Palmer) Smith, and of Joel Palmer's home built in 1852 in Dayton, Oregon; and a daguerreotype of Mrs. Polly Smith, wife of Andrew D. Smith.
Correspondents represented in this collection include George H. Ambrose, Joseph Conant Avery, Daniel F. Bradford, Robert Christie Buchanan, Benjamin Franklin Burch, Asahel Bush, Jacob Comegys, John Winchell Cullen, Anson Dart, Edwin P. Drew, Robert W. Dunbar, William H. Farrar, DeLancey Floyd- Jones, Philip Foster, Charles K. Gardiner, Joseph M. Garrison, Edward Rachford Geary, Joseph Cary Geer, Addison Crandall Gibbs, La Fayette Grover, Edward Hamilton, William Holmes, David S. Holton, Thomas Jefferson Hubbard, David C. Ingalls, Ralph Jacobs, Berryman Jennings, William Sargent Ladd, Joseph Lane, William Jennings Martin, Alfred B. Meacham, James Willis Nesmith, Robert Newell, William Holman Odell, Peter Skene Ogden, Cyrus Olney, Nathan Olney, Ephraim Palmer, Josiah L. Parrish, L. J. Powell, Orville Charles Pratt, John B. Preston, Gabriel James Rains, William W. Raymond, Cyrus Adams Reed, John Fulton Reynolds, Robert Valentine Short, Benjamin Simpson, Alonzo A. Skinner, Andrew Jackson Smith, Edward P. Smith, Henry Harmon Spalding, Charles Carroll Stratton, Christopher Taylor, Chester N. Terry, Robert R. Thompson, William Tichenor, Aaron E. Wait, Courtney M. Walker, Cyrus Hamlin Walker, Joseph Watt and Frederick Waymire.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1956
Indian agents --Oregon --Correspondence.; Pacific Coast Indians, Wars with, 1847-1865.; Americana; West (U.S.); Oregon Territory --History.; Palmer, Joel, 1810-1881.; Palmer, Ephraim; Palmer, Joel, 1810-1881 --Correspondence.; Palmer, Ephraim --Correspondence.; Grover, La Fayette, 1823-1911 --Correspondence.; Buchanan, Robert Christie, 1811-1878 --Correspondence.; Gibbs, A. C. (Addison Crandall), 1825-1886 --Correspondence.; Geary, Edward Ratchford, 1845-1863 --Correspondence.; Stratton, C. C. (Charles Carroll), 1833-1910--Correspondence.; Spalding, Henry Harmon, 1803-1874 --Correspondence.; Walker, Cyrus, 1827-1913 --Correspondence.; Olney, Nathan, 1824-1866 --Correspondence.; Ogden, Peter Skene, 1790-1854 --Correspondence.; Nesmith, James Willis, 1820-1885 --Correspondence.; Meacham, A. B. (Alfred Benjamin), 1826-1882 --Correspondence.; Bush, Asahel, 1824-1913 --Correspondence.; Pratt, Orville C. (Orville Charles), 1819-1891 --Correspondence.; Palmer family.; United States. Office of Indian Affairs. Oregon Superintendency.
- Biographical material (Box 1)
- 1835-1852 (Box 1)
- 1853 (Box 1)
- 1835-1885 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Transcripts of miscellaneous Joel Palmer correspondence and documents
- 1854 Jan.-Mar. (Box 1)
- 1854 Apr.-May (Box 1)
- 1854 June (Box 1)
- 1854 July-Dec. (Box 1)
- Bank book? Ledger? (Box 1)
- 1855 Jan.-May (Box 2)
- 1855 June-July (Box 2)
- 1855 Aug.-Sept. (Box 2)
- 1855 Oct. (Box 2)
- 1855 Nov. (Box 2)
- 1855 Dec. (Box 2)
- 1856 Jan.-Mar. (Box 2)
- 1856 Jan.-Aug. 27 (Box 2)
  Transcript of diary.
- 1856 Apr.-June (Box 2)
- 1856 July-Dec. (Box 2)
- 1857-1859 (Box 2)
- Diary, 1860 (Box 3)
- Diary, 1861 (Box 3)
- 1860 Jan. 1-5 (Box 3)
- 1860 Jan. 5-Nov. 11 (Box 3)
- 1860 Feb.-Dec. (Box 3)
- 1861 Feb. 26-Aug. 17 (Box 3)
- 1862-1864 (Box 3)
- 1865 Jan.-June (Box 3)
- 1865 July-Dec. (Box 3)
- 1866 Jan.-Mar. (Box 4)
- 1866 Apr.-1870 (Box 4)
- 1871 (Box 4)
- 1872-1888 (Box 4)
- undated (Box 4)
- Photograph, ambrotype (Box 4)
- Photograph, daguerrotype (Box 4)
- Holy Bible (Box 5)
- Oversize materials include: (Ovflat 26)
  General
  Plat map of Dayton, Oregon
  Snake River Expedition map, 1855
  Muster Rolls, 1855-1865
  Quarterly Return of Ordnance and Ordnance Stores, 1865-1866
  Inventory and inspection reports, 1865-1866
  Commissioned officer returns, 1865
  Lists of Deserters, 1865
  Palmer's appointment to Superintendent of Indian Affairs by U.S. President Franklin Pierce
  Oregon Superintendency accounts, 1853-1855